Jean Hennebert

Full Professor at University of Applied Sciences Western Switzerland

Résumé

Jean Hennebert is Full Professor and Dean of the Computer Science Department with the University of Applied Science at the Engineering School of Fribourg, HES-SO, Switzerland. Jean is also co-leading the Institute of Complex Systems in Fribourg (iCoSys), in charge of Intelligent Data Analysis group. He is also currently appointed as lecturer and senior researcher in Computer Science at the University of Fribourg. From a research point of view, Jean has developed a strong expertise in Applied Machine Learning and Signal Processing in different areas such as biometrics, biomedical applications, speech applications, electric load modeling and other kind of signals. Jean is also interested in agile IT Project Management and Green-IT developments. Previously, Jean Hennebert has also held the position of Associate Director at Ubilab, the innovation lab of UBS Zurich and was director of technologies with UbiCall Communications SA (Belgium), a company active in automated IT telephony services. He held the position of research scientist at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, Lausanne and was invited researcher at the International Computer Science Institute (Berkeley, USA). Jean Hennebert holds a M.Sc. in Electrical Engineering and Telecommunications (FPMs Mons, Belgium) as well as a Ph.D. from the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (EPFL, Lausanne). Jean Hennebert is the author or co-author of book chapters, scientific journal papers and international conference articles in Computer Science. Specialties: software engineering, agile project management, scrum, signal processing, stochastic modeling, machine learning, biometrics, green-IT

Expérience

Full Professor and Dean , University of Applied Sciences Western Switzerland

2011 - Present (4 years)

I am teaching Master and Bachelor computer science classes in the area of software development, IT project management and Machine Learning. As Dean, I am involved in the management of the Department of Computer Science and in the strategic evolution of the courses. As co-leader of the Institute of Complex Systems in Fribourg, I am also involved in the management of Ra&D activities in domains related to Machine Learning, Big Data and Signal Processing (team of 10 researchers).

Lecturer and Senior Researcher , DIUF / DIVA University of Fribourg

2004 - Present (11 years)

Full time from 2004 to 2007 and part time from 2007 to now, I am working with the Department of Informatics. I am teaching bachelor and master classes in computer science and IT project management. I am also in charge of supervising PhD students in the area of machine learning.

Full Professor, University of Applied Sciences of Western Switzerland

2007 - 2011 (4 years)

I was leading the Software Engineering Unit of the Business Information Systems institute of the HES-SO// Wallis in Sierre. I am teaching computer science classes in the area of software development and IT project management. I am also involved in the management of Ra&D activities in domains related to advanced business IS, green-IT, signal modelling and human-machine interaction.

VP Technology , UbiCall Communications

January 2000 - September 2004 (4 years 9 months)

I co-founded UbiCall Communications, a company offering advanced computer telephony services for telecommunication carriers and enterprises. I was in charge of the technical developments, key accounts and IP matters of the company. As a co-founder and member of the board of director, I had the opportunity to develop experience in company management, team building and fund raising.

System Architect , UBS

1998 - 2000 (2 years)

System Architect with UbiLab, the Innovation Lab of UBS. I have held a position of System Architect with UBS. I was in charge of prototyping and field-testing some of the next generation banking services in English, French and German. I was also in charge of representing UBS for EU research projects.

Invited researcher, ICSI

August 1996 - March 1997 (8 months)

Invited researcher in the speech group. During my Ph.D., I had the opportunity to hold a position of visiting researcher in the International Computer Science Institute of Berkeley, California and to reinforce my knowledge through the large experience of this laboratory in the field of Artificial Neural Networks and pattern recognition.

Researcher, EPFL

1993 - 1995 (2 years)

I started working in Artificial Neural Networks and pattern recognition with the CIRC group (now LANOS group) at EPFL. I took part in several European research projects in team with Lernhout & Hauspie R&D, Ascom Tech and major University laboratories.

Projets

Comodoro Task & Project Manager

novembre 2013 à Poste actuel

Members: Jean Hennebert, Jorge Albaladejo Pomares

Task & Project Management for Micro-Companies. Comodoro lets you effectively pilot your projects, making you more aware of your work in progress. It provides a better insight of the health and status of your ongoing projects, in a glimpse.

CTI Veriname

janvier 2013 à décembre 2014

Members: Jean Hennebert, Baptiste Wicht, Vincenzo Russo, Vincent Raemy, Christophe Gisler

The idea of the project is to leverage on large sets of linguistic data and on machine learning algorithms able to discover automatically pronunciation rules. Such rules are then used in "symbolic mappers" able to transform a grapheme representation into a phonetic representation and to propose probable alterations of the pronunciation. The mappers are then used to propose clients with new domain names that sound similar to their original search.

CTI Veriname

janvier 2013 à décembre 2014

Members: Jean Hennebert, Vincenzo Russo, Baptiste Wicht, Vincent Raemy

The idea of the project is to leverage on large sets of linguistic data and on machine learning algorithms able to discover automatically pronunciation rules. Such rules are then used in "symbolic mappers" able to transform a grapheme representation into a phonetic representation and to propose probable alterations of the pronunciation. The mappers are then used to propose clients with new domain names that sound similar to their original search.

Daplab

août 2015 à Poste actuel

Members: Jean Hennebert, Christophe Bovigny, Benoit Perroud, Vincent Grivel, Jean-François Roche

With a model similar to fablabs, DAPLAB aims at facilitating the access for enterprises and universities to emerging technologies in the area of big data and intelligent data analysis. Many business processes are nowadays generating significant volumes of data that contains valuable information. The main objective of DAPLAB is to reduce the entry barrier for Swiss companies to find value out of their data and ultimately turn into a data-driven company. DAPLAB will answer the needs of educational and economic partners through the integration of analytic algorithms, benchmark data sets and education materials. As a central point of activities, DAPLAB will manage a cluster of servers dedicated to data storage and computation, based on Hadoop and ecosystem, to which universities and companies will have access.

Langues

French English

Compétences et expertise

Computer Science
Machine Learning
Green Computing
Scrum
Agile Project Management
Signal Processing
Software Engineering
Artificial Intelligence
Biometrics
Stochastic Modeling

Project Management

Teaching

Software Development

Algorithms

Java

Matlab

Image Processing

Green IT

Computer Vision

Agile Methodologies

UML

Programming

Natural Language Processing

Pattern Recognition

Speech Recognition

Human Computer Interaction

Artificial Neural Networks

Mathematical Modeling

Neural Networks

Information Retrieval

Data Mining

Formation

Ecole polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

PhD, Computer Science, 1995 - 1998

Faculté Polytechnique de Mons

MSc. in Electrical Engineering, Telecommunication, 1988 - 1993

Centres d'intérêt

signal processing, stochastic modeling, data mining, software engineering, agile methodologies

Certifications

SCRUM Master

Agile Alliance

Jean Hennebert

Full Professor at University of Applied Sciences Western Switzerland



Prenez contact avec Jean sur LinkedIn